Guide to the William Duer Papers 1752-1836 (bulk 1770-1800) MS 182
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
William Duer Papers
1752-1836 (bulk, 1770-1800)
MS 182
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
13.9 Linear feet (12 boxes, 3 volumes)
The Duer papers document William Duer's various mercantile and financial dealings, especially in contracts to outfit the Army during the Revolution, and his subsequent speculations leading to his incarceration in debtors' prison. They also include some correspondence to and from other members of the Duer family.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Biographical Note
The third son of John and Francis (Frye) Duer, William Duer was born in Devonshire, England, on March 18, 1747. After a brief stint as aide-de-camp to Lord Clive in India and a few years of work on the family plantations in the Caribbean, Duer moved to the colony of New York in 1773. Duer had, on a previous trip to the area, purchased tracts of land on the North (Hudson) River near Albany. The area, known as Fort Miller, served both as Duer's first residence and as the site of his early financial ventures. Duer set up sawmills, warehouses, and a store, and, by 1776, had built a moderately successful mercantile business based primarily on lumber production.
A supporter of independence, Duer was an active member of the New York State Convention and went on to serve in the Continental Congress. Duer's public career ended in 1790 when he resigned from the Treasury Department where he had served as assistant secretary under his friend Alexander Hamilton.
Duer, however, gained much more notoriety from his financial dealings than from his contributions as a public servant. One of his first large-scale projects was to supply Continental troops with food during the Revolutionary War. Duer gained real economic stature, however, in the 1780s with his large land and stock speculations. Prominent among them was the Scioto speculation, through which Duer and his associates secured the right to purchase from the United States a large tract of western lands, which they in turn decided to sell chiefly to capitalists abroad, particularly in France and Holland.
Duer found himself severely overextended in the 1790s and he faced financial ruin when a suit was brought against him by the government regarding two unbalanced charges while he was with the treasury board. Unable to satisfy his creditors, Duer was arrested on March 23, 1792, and sent to debtors' prison. Duer's economic ties were so wide in the area that his financial collapse set off the first financial panic in New York City.
Duer remained in prison until his death on May 7, 1799.
He was married to the former Catherine Alexander, daughter of William Alexander, Lord Stirling, a general in the Revolutionary War. They had one son, William Alexander Duer (1780-1858), who later served as president of Columbia College.
Scope and Content Note
The William Duer Papers consist largely of correspondence (in English, with a few letters in French), accounts, contracts, financial documents and legal manuscripts. They are the products of William Duer, his family, and his associates. The bulk relate to financial activities, with far smaller amounts related to Duer's government work, his Revolutionary correspondence, and his personal life.
Parts of the collection have been microfilmed onto four reels; those portions of the collection will be brought to the researcher in microfilm format. In the container list below, folders that have been microfilmed are identified by a three-digit number separated by a hypen (e.g., 1-21), which denotes the reel and folder number where the material can be found. Because the physical collection has been rehoused since it was microfilmed, the physical folder and microfilm folder numbers do not always correspond.
Arrangement
Material within the series is arranged chronologically unless otherwise noted.
The collection is arranged into 19 series:
Series I. Correspondence - William Duer, 1752-1799, Undated
Series II. Correspondence - William Duer with Tench Tilghman, 1776
Series III. Correspondence - Catherine (Mrs. William) Duer, Undated
Series IV. Correspondence - William Alexander Duer, 1816-1824, Undated
Series V. Chancery Cases, 1790-1803, Undated
Series VI. Legal Documents, 1772-1796, Undated
Series VII. Debtors' Prison, 1795-1798, Undated
Series VIII. Poughkeepsie Distillery Papers, 1782-1783, Undated
Series IX. Bonds, Deeds and Leases, 1763-1799, Undated
Series X. Invoices, 1770-1786, Undated
Series XI. Papers Relating to Robert Snell, 1771-1774, Undated
Series XII. Lumber Papers, 1785-1789
Series XIII. Papers Relating to Duer's Siblings, 1769-1829, Undated
Series XIV. Financial Documents, Speculation, 1782-1795, Undated
Series XV. Army Supply Papers, 1781-1785
Series XVI. Accounts, 1781-1792
Series XVII. Bills, Receipts and Notes, 1752-1798, Undated
Series XVIII. Unclassified personal and family materials
Series XIX. Bound volumes
Bird, Mark, 1739-1812.; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789.; Duer family; Duer, Catherine Alexander.; Duer, William Alexander, 1780-1858.; England and Wales. ROyal Navy -- Equipment.; Livingston, Edward, 1764-1836.; New York (State). Court of Chancery.; Peebles, Hugh; Scioto Land Company; Snall, Robert, fl. 1771-1774.; Tilghman, Tench, 1744-1786.; United States. Army -- Supplies and stores.; United States. Continental Army -- Supplies and stores.; Wilson, James, 1742-1798.; Account books; Accounts; Bills of exchange; Contracts; Correspondence; Debt, Imprisonment for -- New York (State.; Deeds; Distilleries -- New York (State) -- Poughkeepsie; Finance -- New York (State); Fort Miller (N.Y.) -- Commerce.; Indentures; Invoices; Jails -- New York (State) -- New York.; Land settlement -- Illinois.; Leases; Legal documents; Letter books; Lumber trade -- United States.; New York (State) -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Equipment and supplies.; Poughkeepsie (N.Y.) -- Commerce; Receipts; Sawmills -- New York (State) -- Fort Miller.; Speculation.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Equipment and supplies.; Vouchers
- Series I. Correspondence: William Duer, 1752-1799, Undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Ranging from his earliest mercantile activities to his last days in debtors' prison, these letters to and from Duer contain a wealth of information pertaining to his financial career. They include, among other topics, descriptions of the work being done at Fort Miller and the Poughkeepsie distillery, Duer's contracts to supply military troops, and land and stock speculation including letters regarding the Scioto company. The papers also include a few letters dealing with Duer's work in public service. There is also a family tree of the English Duers compiled in 1895.
  The correspondence is arranged in chronological order and is available on microfilm.
  - Correspondence (reel 1-1), 1752-1777 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-2), 1777-1781 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-3), 1782 January - June (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-4), 1782 July - August (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (reel (1-5), 1782 September - December (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (and accounts) relating to the Poughkeepsie distillery (reel 1-6), 1782 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-7), 1783 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-8), 1784 January - May (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-9), 1784 June - December (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-10), 1785 January - June (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-11), 1785 July - October (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-12), 1785 November - December (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-13), 1786 January - June (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-14), 1786 July - December (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-15), 1787 January - June (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-16), 1787 July - December (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-17), 1788 January - June (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-18), 1788 July - December (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-19), 1789 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (reel 1-20), 1790 January - May (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-21), 1790 June - August (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-22), 1790 September (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-23), 1790 October (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-24), 1790 November (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-25), 1790 December (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-26), 1791 January - February (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-27), 1791 March - April (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-28), 1791 May - June (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-29), 1791 July - December (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-30), 1792 January - June (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-31), 1792 July - December (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-32), 1793 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-33), 1794 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-34), 1795 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-35), 1796 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-36), 1797-1799 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (reel 2-37), Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series II: Correspondence: William Duer with Tench Tilghman, 1776
  This series contains letters between Tench Tilghman, aide-de-camp to General Washington, and the Committee of Correspondence of the New York State Convention. The purpose of the Committee was to obtain and communicate war intelligence. Duer was a member of this Committee and was the primary writer of letters to Tilghman. The letters from Tilghman contain comprehensive reports on the status of the American troops, the British troops and the progress of the war. Duer's letters contain questions and observations as well as advice on the war. Note: The letters are 1881 copies of 1776 transcripts.
  - Correspondence (reel 1-1A), 1776 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series III. Correspondence: Catherine (Mrs. William) Duer, undated
  These letters deal with family matters and Duer's financial situation.
  - Catherine (Mrs. William) Duer letters (reel 4-38), Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series IV. Correspondence: William Alexander Duer, 1816-1824, undated
  The majority of the correspondence of Duer's son, William Alexander Duer, consists of letters to Hugh Peebles about his financial affairs. The one letter not addressed to Peebles is to John Rutherfurd concerning a speech Duer was to give at the New-York Historical Society on federal and state constitutions.
  - William Alexander Duer correspondence, 1816-1824, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series V. Chancery cases, 1790-1803, undated
  The bulk of these cases were heard in the chancery court of New York during the 1790s. Also included are a few cases from other states. In the majority of cases the direct relationship to Duer is unclear. The New York cases were presided over by Chancellor Robert B. Livingston, Esq. All cases in the collection are incomplete; materials are arranged alphabetically by plaintiff.
  - Chancery cases: Fenwick - Forrester, 1796-1800, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chancery cases: Frean - La Herriere, 1791-1803 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Chancery cases: Laight - Laplante, 1790-1799 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Chancery cases: Law, 1794-1802 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Chancery cases: Lawrence - Leroy, 1795-1800 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chancery cases: Livingston - Schroeppel, 1796-1803, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Chancery cases: Sternbergh, 1797-1801 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chancery cases: Stevens - Watkins, 1793-1800, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series VI. Legal documents, 1772-1796, undated
  This series consists of legal documents relating to Duer, his business associates, and others. The papers include contracts, agreements and indentures, as well as summons, affidavits, court opinions and other documents. They are arranged in chronological order.
  - Legal documents (reel 4-45), 1772-1775 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Legal documents (reel 4-46), 1781-1789 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Legal documents (reel 4-47), 1791-1796, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Series VII. Debtors' Prison, 1795-1798, undated
  Duer was held in debtors' prison from 1792 until his death in 1799. In order to preserve order and harmony there, some of the prisoners established a "court" to hear disputes between prisoners. Certain prisoners were elected "judges." Duer was elected a "judge" in 1797. These papers consist of documents of that court, including the facts in various cases, judgments rendered, court attendance records, and records of the elections of the court officers.
  - Debtors' prison (reel 4-39), 1795-1796 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Debtors' prison (reel 4-40), 1797-1798 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Debtors' prison (reel 4-41), Undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series VIII. Poughkeepsie Distillery papers, 1782-1783, undated
  The series includes bills, receipts, notes and other documents pertaining to Duer's Poughkeepsie Distillery.
  - Poughkeepsie distillery records, 1782-1783, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Series IX. Bonds, deeds, and leases, 1763-1799, undated
  The series contains records of debts owed by and to Duer as well as third-party debt. Deeds and leases pertaining to Duer and others are also included. An earlier inventory noted that Box 6, folder 5, has been microfilmed on reel 4-44, but no such folder is found on the microfilm.
  - Bonds, Deeds, Leases (reel 4-42), 1764-1774 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Bonds, deeds, leases, 1782-1789 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Deeds, leases (reel 4-43), 1795-1799 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Deeds, leases, contracts, illustration of Duer's country home, Fort Miller, 1795-1799, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series X. Invoices, 1770-1786, undated
  The series includes invoices from the entire spectrum of Duer's mercantile involvement.
  - Invoices, 1770-1774 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Invoices, 1781-1785 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Invoices, 1786, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series XI. Papers relating to Robert Snell, 1771-1774, undated
  The series includes accounts, expenditures and other records from Fort Miller, where Robert Snell, an early business associate of Duer's, managed the mercantile activities and lumber mill work. Also included are Duer's papers concerning the debt Snell had incurred while managing Duer's day-to-day business affairs.
  - Papers, 1771-1774, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Series XII. Lumber papers, 1785-1789
  The series includes invoices and other documents relating to Duer's lumber operation, especially the production of ship masts.
  - Lumber papers, 1785-1789 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Series XIII. Papers relating to Duer's siblings, 1769-1829, undated
  The documents in this series involve Duer's siblings. A family tree, wills, information on the family's plantations in the Caribbean, legal papers and other documents are included. The materials are out of chronological order but mirror their order in the microfilmed version.
  - Papers relating to Duer's siblings (reel 4-52), 1783-1829, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Papers relating to Duer's sublings (reel 4-53), 1769-1807 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Series XIV. Financial documents and speculation, 1782-1795, undated
  The series includes financial documents pertaining, for the most part, to Duer's involvement in land, stock, bank notes, and other areas of eighteenth century speculation.
  - Speculations: Bills of exchange, loan office certificates, 1782-1788 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Book of expences [sic](reel 4-48), 1788 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Speculations: Government secutrities, bank stock, loan office certificates (reel 4-49), 1789-1791 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Speculations (reel 4-50), 1792-1795, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Speculations: Scioto speculation and Joseph LeTurc, 1790-1794, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Financial documents, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Series XV. Army supply papers, 1781-1785
  The series contain records and receipts from Duer's contracts to supply divisions of the American army with food and other necessities during and after the Revolutionary War.
  - Army, 1781 January - 1782 March (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Army, 1782 April (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Army, 1782 May (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Army, 1782 June (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Army, 1782 July (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Army, 1782 August (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Army, 1782 September (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Army, 1782 October (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Army, 1782 November - December (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Schenectady, 1782 April - 1783 January (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Army, 1783 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Army, 1784 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Army, 1785 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Series XVI. Accounts, 1781-1792
  The series includes records from various accounts and an account book from Duer's mercantile enterprises. Materials are arranged by name and in approximate chronological order.
  - Accounts: Wycoff and Smith, 1781-1788 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Accounts: Melancton Smith, 1781 December - 1791 July, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Accounts: Hugh McAdam, 1782 February - May (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Accounts: Thompson and Skinner, 1782 February - October (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Accounts: Edward Compston, 1782 May - October (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Accounts: William Hill, 1784-1790 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Accounts: Theodosium Fowler, George and Samuel Douglas, 1785-1790 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Account Book, 1791-1792 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Series XVII. Bills, receipts, and notes, 1752-1798, undated
  The series includes bills, receipts and notes.
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1752-1769 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1771-1774 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1775-1779 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1780-1790 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1782 January - May (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1782 June - December (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1782 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1783 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1784 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1785 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1786 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1787 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1788 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1789 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1790 January - August (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1790 September - December (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1791 January - April (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1791 May - August (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1791 September - December, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1792 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1793 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1794 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, 1795-1798 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes, Undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Bills, receipts, and notes (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Series XVIII. Unclassified business and family material, 1766-1836
  The series includes materials not assigned to other series at the time that the collection was microfilmed, including "…Arrangement to be Made of Mr. Duer's Papers"; "Inventory of Sundry Merchandise Remaining in the Store at Fort Miller on the 13th day of December 1773"; "an Account of Cash Received in the Store at Fort Miller," not dated; an advertisement dated 1766 that announces an upcoming survey; an undated plan for a paper mill; three items related to the donation of a canopy for a lodge in New Jersey, dated 1792 and 1793. Nineteenth century items include two indentures involving W.A. Duer (1807 and 1810) and several pieces of correspondence as well as a listing of items included in the bound volumes (see Series XIX).
  - Items not assigned to a series, 1766-1836, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Calendar of bound volumes I and II (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Series XIX. Bound volumes
  The two volumes of correspondence include letters received by Duer related mostly to supplying the American Army during the Revolution, the Scioto Land Company, and the settlement of Illinois. They are numbered in pencil from 1-138 (volume 1) and 139-257 (volume 2). The timber contracts pertain to agreements with the governments of Spain and France to supply timber for ship masts and spars. Silas Deane, James Wilson, and Mark Bird were also associated with this enterprise. The remainder of this volume appears to have been used for penmanship practice and casual use.
  Volumes 1 and 2 are available on reel 3 of the microfilm.
  - Correspondence (reel 3), 1776-1783 (Volume 1)
  - Correspondence (reel 3), 1784-1802 (Volume 2)
  - Timber contracts, 1774-1779 (Volume 3)